GARDEN 2 days after this, when Mary opened her eyes she sat upright in bed
immediately, and called to Martha. "Look at the mo Look at the
more The rainstorm had ended and the gray mist and clouds had been swept away
in the night by the wind. The wind itself had ceased and a brilliant, deep blue sky
arched high over the Morland Never, never had Mary dreamed of a sky so
blue. In India skies were hot and blazing; this was of a deep cool blue
which almost seemed to sparkle like the waters of some lovely bottomless lake,
and here and there, high, high in the arched bless floated small clouds of Snow White
fleece. The far-reaching world of the Moore itself looked softly blue instead
of gloomy purple black or awful dreary gray I said Martha with a cheerful grin
the storm's over for a bit. It does like this at this time of the year. It goes
off in a night like it was pretending it had never been here and never meant to
come again. That's because the springtime's on its way. It's a long way
off yet, but it's coming I thought perhaps it always rained or looked dark
in England," Mary said a no!" said Martha, sitting up on her heels among her black
Le brushes now of the sort What does that mean?" asked Mary
seriously. In India the natives spoke different dialects which only a few
people understood, so she was not surprised when Martha used words she did
not know. Martha laughed as she had done the first morning. "There now," she said. "I've talked
broad Yorkshire again like Mrs. Medlock said I mustn't now to the sort means
nothing of the sort slowly and carefully, "but it takes so long to say it.
Yorkshire's the sunniest place on earth when it is sunny. I told thee that'd like
the more after a bit. Just you wait till you see the gold colored gor blossoms
and the blossoms of the broom and the heather flowering all purple bells and
hundreds of butterflies fluttering and bees humming and skylars soaring up and
singing You'll want to get out on it at sunrise and live out on it all day like
Dicken does." "Could I ever get there?" asked Mary wistfully, looking through her window at
the far off blue. It was so new and big and wonderful and such a heavenly
color. "I don't know," answered Martha that's never used thy legs since thou
was born, it seems to me that couldn't walk 5 mile. It's 5 mile to our
cottage." "I should like to see a cottage."
Martha stared at her a moment curiously before she took up her polishing brush
and began to rub the grate again. She was thinking that the small plain face did
not look quite as sour at this moment moment as it had done the first morning
she saw it. It looked just a trifle like little Susan an's when she wanted something very
much. "I'll ask my mother about it," she said. "She's one of them that nearly
always sees a way to do things. It's my
day out today and I'm going home. Eh! I am glad. Mrs. Medlock thinks a lot of mother.
Perhaps she could talk to her." "I like your mother," said Mary. "I should think th did," agreed
Martha, polishing away. "I've never seen her," said Mary. "No
that hasn't," replied Martha. She sat up on her heels again and rubbed the end of
her nose with the back of her hand as if puzzled for a moment, but she ended quite
positively. "Well, she's that sensible and hardworking and good-natured and clean
that no one could help liking her whether they'd seen her or not. When I'm
going home to her on my day out I just jump for joy when I'm crossing the moall
I like Dickon," added Mary. "And I've never seen him." "Well," said Martha stoutly, "I've
told thee that the very birds likes him and the rabbits and wild sheep and
ponies and the foxes themselves. I wonder," staring at her
reflectively, "what Dickon would think of thee?" "He wouldn't like me," said Mary in
her stiff, cold little way. "No one does."
Martha looked reflective again. "How does thou like Thy cell she
inquired, really quite as if she were curious to know. Mary hesitated a moment and thought
it over. "Not at all— —really," she answered.
"But I never thought of that before."
Martha grinned a little as if at some homely recollection. "Mother said said that to me
once," she said. "She was at her washtub and
I was in a bad temper and talking ill of folk and she turns around on me and
says Thou young Vixen th There thou stands saying thou doesn't like this one
and thou doesn't like that one. How does thou like Thy cell It made me laugh and
it brought me to my senses in a minute." She went away in high spirits as
soon as she had given Mary her breakfast.
She was going to walk 5 miles across the moall to the cottage, and she was going
to help her mother with the washing and do the week's baking and enjoy herself
thoroughly. Mary felt lonelier than ever when she knew she was no longer in the
house. She went out into the garden as quickly as possible, and the first thing
she did was to run round and round the fountain flower garden 10
times. She counted the times carefully and when she had finished she felt in better
spirits. The sunshine made the whole place look different. The high, deep, blue sky arched
over mistle as well as over the mo and she kept lifting her face and looking up
into it, trying to imagine what it would be like to lie down on one of the little
snow white clouds and float about. She went into the first kitchen
garden and found Ben Weatherstaff working there with two other gardeners.
The change in the weather seemed to have done him good. He spoke to her of his own
accord. "Springtime's coming he said.
"Cannot thou smell it?" Mary sniffed and thought she could. "I smell something nice and fresh
and damp," she said. "That's the good rich earth," he answered, digging away. "It's in a good
humor making ready to grow things. It's glad when planting time comes. It's dull
in the winter when it's gotten out to do.
In the flower gardens out there things will be stirring down below in the dark
the sun's warming them You'll see bits of green spikes sticking out of the black earth after a
bit." "What will they be?" asked Mary.
"Crocuses and snow drops and Daffy Down dillies Has thou never seen them?" "No.
Everything is hot, and wet, and green after the rains in India," said Mary. "And I
think things grow up in a night." "These won't grow up in a night," said weather
staff they'll have to wait for him They'll poke up a bit higher here and
push out a spike more there and uncurl a leaf this day and another that. You watch
them I am going to," answered Mary. Very soon she heard the soft
rustling flight of wings again and she knew at once that the robin had come
again. He was very per and lively, and hopped about so close to her feet, and
put his head on one side and looked at her so slightly that she asked Ben
Weatherstaff a question. "Do you think he remembers me?" she said. "Remembers thee!"
said weather staff indignantly. "He knows every cabage stump
in the gardens, let alone the people. He's never seen a little wench here before
and he's bent on finding out all about thee there's no need to try to hide anything from
him "Are things stirring down below in the dark in that garden where he lives?"
Mary inquired. "What garden?" grunted weather staff becoming surly again. "The one where
the old rose trees are." She could not help asking, because she wanted so much to
know. "Are all the flowers dead, or do some of them come again in the summer? Are are
there ever any roses?" "Ask him," said Ben weather staff
hunching his shoulders towards the robin.
"He's the only one as knows. No one else has seen inside it for 10
years 10 years was a long time, Mary thought. She had been born 10 years ago.
She walked away, slowly thinking. She had begun to like the garden just as she had
begun to like the robin and Dickon and Martha's mother. She was beginning to
like Martha, too. That seemed a good many people to like— —when you were not used to
liking. She thought of the robin as one of the people. She went to her walk
outside the long Ivy covered wall over which she could see the
Treetops and the second time she walked up and down the most interesting and
exciting thing happened to her, and it was all through Ben weather staff's robin.
She heard a chirp and a twitter, and when she looked at the bare flower bed at her
left side there he was hopping about and pretending to peck things out of the
earth to persuade her that he had not followed her. But she knew he had followed her and
the surprise so filled her with delight that she almost trembled a little. "You do
remember me!" she cried out. "You do! You are prettier than than anything else in the
world!" She chirped, and talked, and coaxed and he hopped, and flirted his tail and
twittered. It was as if he were talking. His red waste coat was like
satin and he puffed his tiny breast out and was so fine and so grand and so
pretty that it was really as if he was showing her how important and like a
human person a robin could be. Mistress Mary for for got that she had ever been
contrary in her life when he allowed her to draw closer and closer to him, and
bend down and talk and try to make something like robin sounds. Oh! to think that he should
actually let her come as near to him as that! He knew nothing in the world would
make her put out her hand toward him or startle him in the least tiniest way. He
knew it because he was a real person— —only nicer than any other person in the world.
She was so happy that she scarcely dared to breathe. The flower bed was not quite
bare. It was bare of flowers because the perennial plants had been cut down for
their winter rest, but there were tall shrubs and low ones which grew together
at the back of the bed, and as the robin hopped about under them she saw him hop
over a small pile of freshly turned up earth. He stopped on it to look for a
worm. The the earth had been turned up because a dog had been trying to dig up
a mole and he had scratched quite a deep hole. Mary looked at it, not really
knowing why the hole was there, and as she looked she saw something almost
buried in the newly turned soil. It was something like a ring of
rusty iron or brass and when the robin flew up into a tree nearby she put out
her hand and picked the ring up. It was more more than a ring, however; it was an
old key which looked as if it had been buried a long time. Mistress Mary stood
up and looked at it with an almost frightened face as it hung from her
finger. "Perhaps it has been buried for 10 years," she said in a
whisper. "Perhaps it is the key to the
garden!" CHAPTER 8 THE ROBIN WHO SHOWED